this is from the
nikaya book of sixes verse 13
it's called the elements of escape i'll
just read the first
first one
because there are these six elements of
escape what's six so just the first one
what's six so just the first one
take a biku who says i've frequently
practiced and developed
a liberated mind through
non-ill will or meta
i've cultivated cultivated it made it my
vehicle and my basis kept it up
consolidated it
and properly implemented it yet somehow
ill will still occupies my mind
that beku should be told it's impossible
not so
venomous don't say that don't
misrepresent the buddha for
misrepresentation of the buddha is not
good and the buddha would not say that it is
and the buddha would not say that it is
impossible
it cannot happen that the mind liberated
through non-illegal or matter
which has been developed would still be
occupied by your will for it is the mind that is
by your will for it is the mind that is
liberated to non-evil
that is the escape from will yeah that's
it's exactly the same principle of when
we said
many times before but i don't know what
the dhamma is as in
i'm not a sort of partner but i'm
practicing the dharma
how's that possible no matter means
non-ill will
so if you're practicing matter your will
cannot be arising
so it means i can i cannot do matter
if i'm not free from it no means don't
think you're doing matter
you should keep trying to do matter but
don't think that's the matter
for as long as you're having your will
you should be trying to practice the
dharma but don't think that's the dhamma
for as long as you're not assaulted
that's the whole point
and that's exactly because people think
oh so i shouldn't do this
no do it just don't think that it is
what it isn't
so because if i think i know i'm doing
the matter that's good enough you're not
going to make anything to find out what
the real matter is
they will prevent your will from arising
because it stops if you read what
one moment of meta practice is like
vast amounts of merit so yeah i practice
meta yeah
there you go i'm already set so but i
play this matter
but is my mind like do i know um
the non-original will can i maintain the
mind can i prevent evil from arising do i
can i prevent evil from arising do i
do i see like oh my mind is free from
your will now but
kenyal will arise oh i don't know
yes you can if you don't know means he
can same like the way we say not just that
same like the way we say not just that
you're restrained withdraw from
centrality you have to keep the context over your
you have to keep the context over your
mind whereby
oh can non-reason centrality arise
in different circumstances as in am i
still liable to centrality
if the answer is yes means you're not
practicing fully
rightly correctly you haven't understood
the escape from it
so how can i am practicing this
capability but i don't really know what
escape essentiality is
so i am practicing free from your will
but mind throughout that time remains
liable to future real will
means you're still within the domain of
ill will but that's a good thing to know
exactly so the problem is not in what
you're doing in terms of attempting your
practice or the problem is not solely
based on that the problem is simply you
thinking that it is the matter
because it is full freedom from
sensuality even momentarily
because to that extent you won't search
for what real
matter is and to that extent you will
block your own development
you won't be striving further you won't
be striving for anything
and people would be usually too keen
to to jump onto oh yeah this is the
dhamma although i'm not a sort of
partner yes this is meta although
i am liable to future real world i'm
practicing methods because i'm angry
well they will jump onto that because
it's very kind of uncomfortable
to keep maintaining the notion that
there is more there is more this is not
enough this is not enough this is not
enough so then you just oh but this is enough
so then you just oh but this is enough
because look my life's much better now
yeah but are you liable to future real
world yes means it's not the matter that
the world was teaching that results in
enlightenment because if it were you would have been
because if it were you would have been
enlightened by now
but if you haven't given up given into
that just that little
oh but it's enough this is the matter
it's good enough matter as in it
protects to that which matter
actually is if you haven't given up just
because of that discomfort
you would have actually effortlessly
forced yourself in the direction of
progress in directional development simply by not
in directional development simply by not
covering up
the obvious truth i can't practice the
dhamma unless i know what the dhamma is
for myself free from doubt
so it's good to air on the side of well
maybe this is not
always exactly always because there's
nothing to lose harder let me
look deeper into this yeah and you you
you you revise that but okay this is
matter for me at the moment
but is that the matter that the buddha
said matter is
then you read what the buddha said
matter is what resulted
what results in to what extent it goes
and then you compare to
to where you are at so am i am i liable
to future your will
yes means this what i have so nobody
denies what you have feels good
it's probably useful to some extent but
just don't think
that it is what the buddha was talking
about because if it were
you would be enlightened you would be
liberated as that line said
but if you say it is what the buddha
said but i'm not liberated
you're misrepresenting the bullet airing
on the side of caution doesn't mean
perpetually keeping yourself in a state
of doubt because i'm not sure
certain about anything means recognizing
what certainty you have
and then questioning that certainty
further until you're more certain about
it
because sometimes people okay so i
mustn't jump into conclusions
so i will not discriminate anything i
come across well this might be fine
well this might be fine well that might
be fine this works for me there were no
universal truth the dhamma is the
universal truth
which means it's true in every scenario
for every individual
freedom from suffering is always freedom
from suffering so it's not about
not committing to any direction because
that's all the direction itself you
committed oh i will not commit to an
interaction but it's more like recognizing as i said
but it's more like recognizing as i said
what you already know what you're
already doing
and just not taking it for granted and
questioning it further that same thing
not dismissing it or or i will not
commit to it because maybe it's wrong
yeah everything is wrong for a petuna
you have to commit to something
so the problem is not committing to a
wrong thing the problem is committing
the wrong thing and then not questioning
the wrongness of it or
abandoning the commitment to it so i've
understood mental practice as one thing but how is
mental practice as one thing but how is
this
and how will it free me from being
liable to your will
exactly exactly and instead of
now reading what matters for you
into the suttas you want to do other way
around and you shouldn't be afraid of
questioning your
practice because that which is right
well you should not be
undermining being afraid is not a matter
of choice you will be afraid
so you shouldn't be afraid yeah you
shouldn't but you will be afraid
because you're undermining the very
basis and that's exactly what that's what i
and that's exactly what that's what i
meant that's why people
don't do it and it's good enough because
just that slight undermining reveals
that underlying anxiety that you might be
underlying anxiety that you might be
wrong and all of your efforts
might become might have been completely
misguided but then you if you actually
but then you if you actually
don't give in to that fear they will
have to arise
on account of questioning the very core
of your whole commitment and everything
you will realize that actually no this
is why i'm liable to fear and everything
else because i haven't been questioning
this so even if you spread these 30 years of
so even if you spread these 30 years of
of your practice wrongly
the true reason why that practice was
wrong is because you never questioned
that core
of it but the day you start questioning
the core of it even if it's after 30
years of wrong practice
everything will be made right yeah so i
was trying to say it's
in testing you're testing yourself
testing your understanding
remember that suitable says that i treat
the buddha says to the
i treat monks like a clay like a pot of
trees now just have to define the testing
now just have to define the testing
testing does not mean exposing yourself
to the
circumstances that compromise your
precepts or your seclusion
oh i need to test myself no testing
means reviewing your mind
so oh like i i established my mind in
meta and i'm practicing meta okay now
and i'm practicing meta okay now
question whether that
that is meta don't just take it for
granted and then do this matter you're
practicing but instead question whether that is
but instead question whether that is
matter that you're practicing
so that's it's it's that it's that first
point you read the suit that you hear the
you read the suit that you hear the
teaching you get the idea and then you
start doing things on account of the
idea without questioning the idea then you
without questioning the idea then you
have the other group of people
who now realize they need to question
the idea so they stop doing the idea
because they're not sure about the idea
no you want to do the idea you go you
recognize that is the level you that is
the extent you got from it
you want to do it but at the same time
you want to keep the context that that
idea might
change might be wrong and might need
further development
and then you will remain in the middle
you will not be blindsided by your own
refusal to question it because it's
uncomfortable and reveals the anxiety
on account of that which you invested
effort in already
nor will you go to that extreme and then
not commit to anything because you're
not sure about anything
like you're already committing to
exactly you start somewhere
i must only do good things okay yeah
okay yeah
so you start doing good things you start
keeping the precept and then the idea
behind that you start questioning it while
that you start questioning it while
still keeping the preset so you're not
oh i need to change no no
this is not questionable this is
not up for debate precepts must be kept
sensitive strain must be developed
i don't understand why oh so that's the
idea i need to work on
while i maintain these practices that's
what the testing of yourself is
yeah you shouldn't be afraid of that
testing because it can only upgrading
it's not
yeah you will be afraid yeah but sorry
yeah but you shouldn't be no that's exactly
but you shouldn't be no that's exactly
what people don't do it because of fear
and it's not that i mean it's not a
matter of choice the anxiety is
unpleasant and that's why you don't
question it
so you will be afraid and that's what
the practice is
to accept that anxiety that concern
that our knees about basically like
you know shaking up moving around seeing
what's going to fall out and break on
account of your own very core of your
views and values
without doing the opposite of those
cores and values that's where the
precepts the behavior that has been following the
the behavior that has been following the
precepts and sense restraint
needs to be developed beforehand because
once you start
sort of sieving through these values and
revisiting them
that behavior is already as a habit
established the behavior of not like
five precepts eight precepts
things you don't do
but if you start questioning the values
of the presets before you started
keeping the precepts
or you will be left and right you're not
going to be
keeping anything it's going to be say no
to everything and say yes to everything
just as the mind flips so that's why you
need to
first sustain yourself in the lifestyle
of presets
sense restraint and then these layers of
development will become more apparent
so you can start questioning the values
of it without needing to go into the
opposite of that preset
because the precept is not up for
question it's your value of it
so keeping the precepts is the behavior
that must be maintained
why that's now for you to discern
but once people start questioning why do
i need oh so i don't need to and then go
and break the preset
that's the start yeah exactly not a good start
start
so same like whether it's meta practice
free from ill will all of that requires
you to
okay so i'm not engaging with your will
but if that were the practice of matter
i would be free from future real world i
would not be liable to ill will i would
be outside of the domain of the
possibility of ill will manifesting in
my experience
but i'm not there which means my
practice is the level i am at but that's not the
is the level i am at but that's not the
matter that should be developed
because the matter the good asset should
be developed is the one that frees you
from your will
through and through
and that's all you need to do keep
practicing that level just don't
conflate the two
because conflating will be done on
account of that fear and anxiety
of questioning that your matter might
not be the matter
that the buddha talks about or when
people say you can be another hunt
and and still engage with sensuality
right yes it's the same thing
impossible and again those people will
not do it because
they're malicious and intentionally want
to misrepresent the buddha no they just
genuinely believe that the level they're at
believe that the level they're at
because it feels right for them and
that's their criteria
not the criteria that buddha said should
be such as freedom from suffering
freedom from liability to
lust ill build distraction no it just
feels right
i'm practicing rightly and at the same
time i am engagement sexuality so my
experience is the criteria of what's
right so they make a statement such as
you can practice for our handshake and
not be free from centrality
on account of doing the buddhist
practice it's like well wait is it your
criteria of the buddhist criteria
then you read the buddhist criteria he
said the opposite of which you're
claiming you can't engage with sensuality and
you can't engage with sensuality and
practice for our hanship at the same
time mutually exclusive so you can either
mutually exclusive so you can either
ignore that or not read the suttas and
claim your practice in the buddhist
teaching and then just follow your own criteria
and then just follow your own criteria
create theory of the ignorant mind
the mind that shines away from that
anxiety or questioning
and um and like by the mind that
basically when undermines the value
undermines the behavior of the value
so then just flip-flops between the
presets and non-presets